Guide to the Rosalie Thorne McKenna Papers, 1948-1983
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Rosalie Thorne McKenna Papers
1948-1983
McKenna, Rosalie Thorne
1.5 cubic feet (6 boxes)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
The collection consists primarily of photographs taken by American photographer Rosalie Thorne "Rollie" McKenna (1918-2003) that document life and events at Vassar College during the 1950s and 1960s, including contact sheets, negatives, and prints. It also includes photographs taken by McKenna of Springside National Historic Site, Matthew Vassar's former estate in Poughkeepsie, as well as correspondence with the National Park Service.
Biographical Note
Rosalie Thorne "Rollie" McKenna was an American photographer, best known for her portraits of notable poets, authors, and artists. Born in 1918 in Houston, Texas, McKenna spent the majority of her childhood and adolescence moving around the United States to stay with different relatives. In 1936, she began attending Vassar College, where she graduated in 1940 with a degree in history. She served in the U.S. Navy for several years during World War II and afterwards returned to Vassar in 1948 to pursue a Master's in Art History. She spent the subsequent decades as an independent photographer specializing in architectural and portrait photography. As a photographer, McKenna is best known for her portraits of writers and artists, including poets T.S. Eliot and Elizabeth Bishop, artists Laura Gilpin and John Minton, as well as conductor Leonard Bernstein and actor James Earl Jones. Exhibitions of her work were featured at the National Portrait Galleries in Washington, D.C. and London. McKenna eventually settled down in Stonington, Connecticut in the 1980s and died in Northampton, Massachusetts in 2003 at the age of 84.
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists primarily of photographs taken by American photographer Rosalie Thorne "Rollie" McKenna (1918-2003) that document life and events at Vassar College during the 1950s and 1960s, including contact sheets, negatives, and prints. McKenna also photographed "Springside," Matthew Vassar's former estate in Poughkeepsie, New York, in cooperation with the National Park Service. These photographs are included with Springside's entry in the National Register of Historic Places.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into two series: Series I. Poughkeepsie, New York, 1948-1969; and Series II. Vassar College, 1948-1983.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the
regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library
without any additional restrictions.
Related Materials
The Frances Lehman Loeb Art Museum at Vassar College possesses a collection of McKenna's photographic prints..
The largest collection of McKenna's work is the Rosalie Thorne McKenna Collection (AG 228) at the Center for Creative Photography, University of Arizona in Tucson, Arizona.
Springside Landscape Restoration Records, Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries.
Subject Headings
Organizations:
National Historic Landmarks Program (U.S.); Vassar College
Subjects:
Photographers--United States; Women photographers--United States
Places:
Poughkeepsie (N.Y.)
Document Types:
Contact sheets; Correspondence; Negatives (photographs); Photographs
VCL Categories:
Art and Artists; Local History; Vassar College
Encoding Information
Encoded by Emma Gronbeck, September 2024.
Acquisition Information
Acquired from the Rosalie Thorne McKenna Foundation via Hemenway and Barnes LLP. (M2012-009)
Series List
- Series I. Poughkeepsie, New York, 1948-1969
  This series contains correspondence and photographic materials related to "Springside"--Matthew Vassar's estate--and its designation as a National Historic Site, as well as photographic materials and writings related to Poughkeepsie's Waterfront Park.
  This series is arranged alphabetically by title.
- Series II. Vassar College, 1948-1983
  This series contains negatives, contact sheets, and photographic prints related to Vassar College, including campus architecture, events, students, classes, faculty, and alumnae. Some printed materials related to McKenna's work are also included.
  This series is organized into three subseries by format, and sub-arranged alphabetically by title.
Container List
- Series I. Poughkeepsie, New York, 1948-1969
  - Springside National Historic Landmark - Correspondence and clippings, 1967-1969 (Folder 1.1)
  - Springside National Historic Landmark - Contact sheets, 1968 (Folder 1.2)
  - Springside National Historic Landmark - Negatives, 1968 (Folder 1.3)
  - Springside National Historic Landmark - Photographs (black-and-white), 1968 (Folder 1.4)
  - Springside National Historic Landmark - Photographs (color), 1968 May (Folder 1.5)
  - Waterfront, contact sheets, 1948 (Folder 1.6)
  - "Waterfront Park, Poughkeepsie, NY" by Rollie McKenna - Proposal and correspondence, 1949-1952 (Folder 1.7)
- Series II. Vassar College, 1948-1983
  - Negatives and Contact Sheets
    - 100th Anniversary Day (VAD6.1161), 1961 Jan; [contact sheets only] (Folder 1.8)
    - 100th Anniversary Day (VAD6.1161), 1961 Jan; [negatives only] (Folder 4.1)
    - Alumnae, 1954 (Folder 4.2)
    - Alumnae: Quinn / Sanford / Thornton, undated (Folder 1.9)
    - Alumnae / Professors, undated (Folder 1.10)
    - Alumnae, reunion (?), graduation (?) (#8225), undated (Folder 1.11)
    - Alumnae House, undated; [contact sheets only] (Folder 1.12)
    - Alumnae House; students playing cards in Main, 1955 (Folder 1.13)
    - Alumnae Reunion (#5899), undated; [contact sheets only] (Folder 1.14)
    - Alumnae Reunion (#73482), undated; [contact sheets only] (Folder 4.3)
    - [Alumnae Reunion?], undated; [contact sheets only] (Folder 1.15)
    - [Alumnae Reunion?] (VC1.1361), undated; [contact sheets only] (Folder 1.16)
    - Art Class, 1956 Feb; [negatives only] (Folder 1.17)
    - Art Class (VC101463), 1963 Oct 14 (Folder 4.4)
    - Art Class / Art Opening (VC42964), 1964 Apr 29 (Folder 4.5)
    - Art Conference Class with Barbara Knowles, 1955 Nov (Folder 4.6)
    - Breukelmann, Anne (VC 1958; taken for article "Anne Goes to Vassar"), 1954; [contact sheets only] (Folder 1.18)
    - Campbell, [Mildred] (History Professor), undated (Folder 1.19)
    - Campus (VC101463), 1963 Oct 14 (Folder 1.20)
    - Campus and students, undated (Folder 1.21)
    - Campus and students / Art Class / Library / Tennis (#7892), undated (Folder 1.22)
    - Chadwick, [John B.] (Physiology Professor), undated; [negatives only] (Folder 1.23)
    - Chapel, 1956 Sep (Folder 1.24)
    - Chemistry Class, 1955 Nov (Folder 1.25)
    - Chemistry Class / Ferry House Sitting Room / Applied Sculpture Class, 1955 Nov (Folder 4.6)
    - Chicago House, 1959, 1963 (Folder 4.7)
    - Class with Ted Evck / Campus Pub, 1955 Jun (Folder 4.8)
    - Class with Ted Evck / Main Interior, 1955 Sep (Folder 1.26)
    - Classes, undated; [negatives only] (Folder 1.27)
    - Conservation Work, undated; [contact sheets only] (Folder 1.28)
    - "Co-Op Kids", undated (Folder 1.29)
    - Couch, Helen (VC 1924), undated (Folder 5.1)
    - Davies, Mary, undated (Folder 1.30)
    - Dickenson, George S. "Dickey" (Music Professor), undated (Folder 1.31)
    - Dining Hall / Coed gathering / Musical performance, undated (Folder 5.2)
    - Downer, Henry E. (College Horticulturist), undated (Folder 1.32)
    - Drama (Founder's Day?) (#7511), undated (Folder 1.33)
    - Drama - Junior Party Rehearsal, 1955 Nov (Folder 1.34)
    - Drama and Dance, 1956, undated (Folder 5.3)
    - [Education program?], undated (Folder 1.35)
    - Education Program with Children, 1954 Jan (Folder 5.4)
    - Egan, Patricia (VC 1939, Art Faculty), 1960; [negatives only] (Folder 1.36)
    - Egerton, Judy (in London), 1960 (Folder 1.37)
    - Foster, [Frances Allen] (English Professor), undated (Folder 1.38)
    - [Founder's Day?] (#7660), undated (Folder 2.1)
    - Founder's Day / Matthew Vassar's grave / campus / art class (#7511), undated (Folder 2.2)
    - Fuller, Roy, 1969 (Folder 5.1)
    - Graduation (#7511, #8224, #8225), undated (Folder 5.5)
    - Graduation - Commencement (VAG I-VII), 1959 Jun (Folder 5.6)
    - Graduation - Daisy chain girls (#8095), 1953; [contact sheets only] (Folder 2.3)
    - Grief-Mann Wedding, undated (Folder 5.1)
    - Holmes, John (Administrator), undated (Folder 2.4)
    - Inauguration (President Blanding) and Graduation (VC101664), 1964 Oct 16; [negatives only] (Folder 5.7)
    - Inauguration (President Blanding) and Graduation, with caption list (VC101664), 1964 Oct 16; [contact sheets only] (Folder 2.5)
    - Kitchens, 1956 Feb 3; [negatives only] (Folder 2.6)
    - Library, 1963 Oct (Folder 2.7)
    - Library / Chapel / Bicycles (#7511), circa 1956; [negatives only] (Folder 2.8)
    - Lotz, Wolfgang (Art Professor), undated (Folder 2.9)
    - Main Building, 1948; [contact sheets only] (Folder 2.10)
    - Masters, Marcia Lee, 1969 (Folder 2.11)
    - Meade, Elizabeth "Betty" (VC 1924; Art Professor), undated; [negatives only] (Folder 2.12)
    - Miller, [Maria Tastevin?] (French Professor), undated (Folder 2.13)
    - Observatory / Library, 1963 Oct, undated (Folder 5.8)
    - Professors, 1955 (Folder 2.14)
    - Professors, 1961 Jan (Folder 5.1)
    - Professors, undated (Folder 2.15)
    - Professors, undated; [contact sheets only] (Folder 2.16)
    - Sague, Mary Landon (Chemistry Professor), undated (Folder 2.17)
    - Science Class (VCS10.362), 1962 Mar 10 (Folder 2.18)
    - Seminar with Lillian Smith, 1955 Nov (Folder 5.4)
    - Sophomore Conference (VC9-54), 1954 Sep (Folder 5.9)
    - Stewart, Edith (Administrator), undated (Folder 2.19)
    - Student Athletics (V2.960), undated; [contact sheets only] (Folder 2.20)
    - Student Candy Smith studying in Library, 1955 Nov (Folder 2.21)
    - Vassar Brothers Hospital, child patients, 1954 (Folder 2.22)
    - Vassar Girls / Hotel Lexington, undated; [negatives only] (Folder 2.23)
    - Wedding preparations, undated; [negatives only] (Folder 2.24)
    - Williams, [Hermine Weigel?] (Music Professor), undated (Folder 2.25)
    - Wimpfheimer Nursery School, 1955 Nov (Folder 2.26)
    - Unidentified individual (#8023), 1953 (Folder 2.27)
  - Photographic Prints
    - 100th Anniversary Day (VAD6.1161), 1961 Jan (Folder 2.28)
    - 100th Anniversary Day, 1961 Jan; [11 x 14 prints] (Folder 6.1)
    - Alumnae House, undated (Folder 2.29)
    - Alumnae Reunion, 1953 (Folder 2.30)
    - Alumnae Reunion, [1953?] (Folders 2.31-2.32)
    - Alumnae Reunion - Class of 1940, undated (Folder 2.33)
    - Art Classes / Art Conference, 1955, undated (Folder 2.34)
    - Breukelmann, Anne (for Seventeen Magazine story, "Anne goes to Vassar"), 1954 (Folder 2.35)
    - Campus buildings, undated (Folder 2.36)
    - Campus buildings, 1951, undated; [11 x 14 prints] (Folder 6.2)
    - Chapel, 1956 Sep (Folder 2.37)
    - Chemistry Class, 1955 Nov (Folder 2.38)
    - Chicago House (Foreign Language Class?), 1959 Apr (Folder 2.39)
    - Classes, undated (Folder 2.40)
    - Conservation Work, undated (Folder 3.1)
    - Co-Op / Kitchen / Housekeeping, undated (Folder 3.2)
    - Drama and Dance, 1955-1956, undated (Folder 3.3)
    - Foster, [Frances Allen] (English Professor), undated (Folder 3.4)
    - [Founder's Day?] (#7660), undated (Folder 3.5)
    - Graduation, 1953 (Folder 3.6)
    - Graduation, 1959 (Folder 3.7)
    - Graduation, undated (Folder 3.8)
    - Graduation - Daisy chain girls (#8095), 1953 (Folder 3.9)
    - Graduation - Daisy chain girls - Olivia Maldonado (VC 1955), 1953; [11 x 14 print] (Folder 6.3)
    - Library, undated (Folder 3.10)
    - Main Building, 1955, undated (Folder 3.11)
    - Professors, 1951, undated (Folder 3.12)
    - Science Class (VCS10.362), 1962 Mar 10 (Folder 3.13)
    - Student Athletics, undated (Folder 3.14)
    - Students - Classes of 1955 and 1956, 1952 (Folder 3.15)
    - Students Around Campus, undated (Folder 3.16)
    - Students cycling, undated (Folder 3.17)
    - Vassar Brothers Hospital, child patients, 1954 (Folders 3.18-3.19)
    - Vassar Brothers Hospital, child patient, 1954; [11 x 14 print] (Folder 6.3)
    - Wimpfheimer Nursery School / Education Program, 1954-1955 (Folder 3.20)
  - Printed Material
    - "Anne Goes to Vassar," Seventeen Magazine, clipping, 1955 Mar (Folder 6.4)
    - "Photo-collecting at Vassar: 100 years + 10," catalogue, 1983 (Folder 3.21)
    - Vassar College Alumnae Magazine, 1950 Jun (Folder 3.22)